Margo Nowicka

I am a new media visual artist and animator.

My artistic and research interests reside in the formation of the self at the edges of consciousness and humanity — in meeting other people, and machines. I mainly focus on the themes of social anxiety and humanist anxiety in the age of computational-technological determinism.

I come from Wrocław, Poland and am currently based in Helsinki, Finland.

Artistic portfolio: margonowicka.com

Programming portfolio: github.com/nowickam

Contact: mngnowicka@gmail.com

Education

MA in New Media, Aalto University

2021-2023 | Espoo, Finland

Highest grade (5) for the MA thesis "Aurinko and Selene: Conceptual influences of computation in culture and science through the lens of Finnish genetic study": https://urn.fi/URN:NBN:fi:aalto-202312037039.

Student exchange in Information and Communication Technology, Kungliga Tekniska Högskolan 2018-2020 | Stockholm, Sweden

BSc in Computer Science, Warsaw University Of Technology

2017-2021 | Warsaw, Poland

Summa cum laude with the BSc thesis "Audio-driven facial animation" implementing machine learning approach to algorithmically generate convincing facial animation for human speech.

Warsaw University of Technology Rector's scholarship for high academic performance for 2020/21.

Experience

Animation Director and Exhibition Designer

2.2024-4.2024 | Department of Art and Media, Aalto University, Espoo, Finland Direction of the 2D short animation "Aurinko and Selene" as a part of an upcoming exhibition on the collaboration between the Information Design focus group at Aalto University and Finngen genetic research project.

https://infodesign.aalto.fi/collaboration/

Projection Designer in the "Rottien pyhimys" musical

2.2023-5.2023, 1.2024-2.2024 | Musiikkiteatteri Kapsäkki, Helsinki, Finland

Design of the stage projections for a musical directed by Reetta Ristimäki based on the novel by Anneli Kanto. TouchDesigner interactive projections and formal grammar visualisation.

https://www.gretatuotanto.fi/rottien-pyhimys

Generative Video Designer in the "Ihmisen jälkeen / Posthuman" chamber opera

1.2023-3.2023 | Dance House Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland

Video production for an experimental chamber opera written and directed by Temu Mäki in collaboration with composer Max Savikangas. Generative and artificial life simulations, 3D animation.

https://www.teemumaki.com/theater-posthuman.html

Animation Director for "Takeoff" slam poetry performance

12.2022 - 9.2023 | Department of Art and Media, Aalto University, Espoo, Finland

Direction a short animation visualizing a poem by Giovanni Baudonck using 3D procedural modeling.

Presented in the Prima Vista Literary Festival as an immersive slam poetry performance in the planetarium in Tartu, Estonia. Official Selection in ZEBRA Poetry Film Festival 2023 and Open Call Winner in Kinomural 2023. https://ap-arts.be/en/research/urban-travel-machines

Lecturer and Teaching Assistant

10.2022-12.2022 | Department of Art and Media, Aalto University, Espoo, Finland

Teaching of an introductory course on web development for visual communication students and assistance in teaching a creative coding course.

Research Assistant in a science communication project

6.2022-8.2022 | Department of Art and Media, Aalto University, Espoo, Finland

Visualization of the human genome analysis data for a scrollytelling website as a part of the genetic research project FinnGen.

https://geneviz.aalto.fi/what-is-finngen

Animation Director for "Dysmorphia"

6.2022-9.2023 | Department of Art and Media, Aalto University, Espoo, Finland

Direction of a 3D short animation on the themes of self image and social anxiety.

Received the Department of Art and Media grant for traveling to the Fredrikstad Animation Festival 2022.

Presented in Spring Demo Day 2022, Aalto Media Lab

https://medialabdemoday.aalto.fi/2022-spring/dysmorphia/.

Official Selection in:

Fredrikstad Animation Festival 2022, Fredrikstad, Norway,

15th Annual Short Story Film Festival, Bethel CT, United States,

23. Animatricks International Animation Festival, Helsinki, Finland,

17th Anim! Arte - International Student Animation Festival of Brazil, Rio De Janeiro, Brazil,

Kinomural 2023 Open Call, Wrocław Poland.

Research Assistant in Natural Computation research group

7.2020-9.2020, 7.2021-9.2021, 11.2021-5.2022 | Department of Computer Science, Aalto University, Espoo, Finland

Scientific visualization of the interactions between DNA strands utilizing algorithmic and graph-theoretic approach.

"Automated Rendering of DNA Strand Displacement Systems" poster presentation in the International Conference on Unconventional Computation and Natural Computation, Espoo, Finland and the 29th International Conference on DNA Computing and Molecular Programming, Sendai, Japan. https://arxiv.org/pdf/2308.06392.pdf

Skills

3D animation (Blender, Maya),
2D animation (TVPaint),
generative programming (Processing, p5js, GLSL, openFrameworks),
web development (HTML, CSS, JavaScript, React),
data visualization (D3.js, THREE.js),
audiovisual exhibition and performance (TouchDesigner, PureData, Python, C++, Adobe Premiere),
electronics (Arduino, Bela),
programming (C, C++, C#, Python, Java, JavaScript)

Languages

Polish native English fluent German basic